Finding Aid for Alfred B. Connable papers 1925-1992 (bulk 1941-1957)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alfred B. Connable papers 1925-1992, 1941-1957
Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-
2 linear feet
Republican regent of the University of Michigan. Files and photographs relating to his election campaigns, his regental activities, especially as member of the Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions; also papers concerning his work as price specialist with the Office of Price Administration during World War II, and as Michigan campaign manager for Wendell Willkie, 1943-1944.
8595 Aa 2 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Alfred B. Connable, Jr. (Donor No. 2541 ) in 1977 and June 1992.
The collection is open for research.
Alfred B. Connable, Jr. served as a regent of the University of Michigan for sixteen years beginning in 1941. Connable, who was born in Kalamazoo, Michigan on February 20, 1904, graduated from the University of Michigan in 1925. After completing a master's degree in business administration from Harvard University in 1929, he embarked on a career that included both business and political achievements.
Connable was chairman of the board of the Monroe Calculating Machine Company, which was founded by his father and several other University of Michigan alumni. Connable also worked with the Detroit Trust Company, and taught investments and economics at the Detroit Institute of Technology. In 1943, he began Connable Associates, a financial services office. In the political arena, Connable was Wendell L. Willkie's Michigan campaign manager, and was involved in Republican party activities for many years.
While a regent of the university, Connable's activities included membership and presidency of the Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions. He was also involved in the labor education program called the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations. The Institute, under joint sponsorship of the University of Michigan and Wayne State University, was committed to serving the educational and research needs of both labor and management through the combined resources of the universities.
The papers in the Alfred B. Connable collection, covering the years 1925-1992, document Connable's political and business careers, and also include biographical information. Included in the collection are newspaper clippings, correspondence, a diary, and photographs. The collection is organized into six series: Biographical Information, Board of Regents, Business Career, Political Career, Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions.; Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-; Universities and colleges--United States.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Office of Price Administration.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; World War, 1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-; Fairlane (Dearborn, Mich.); Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-2015; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Office equipment industry.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Dearborn.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; North Campus (University of Michigan)
Contributors:
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre/Form:
Panoramic views.; Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information includes newspaper clippings from throughout Connable's life, information about family, and a personal journal of his trip to South America in 1925. In addition, transcripts from interviews taped in 1986 by Russell Strong are included. These interviews cover most of Connable's life, ranging from discussions on business and his career as a University of Michigan Regent, to his family and interests in music and travel.
  - Personal (Box 1)
  - Transcripts of reminiscences taped in 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Diary of South American Trip 1925 (Box 1)
    (includes clippings, memorabilia)
- Board of Regents
  Board of Regents, the second series, is divided into Campaign Files (1939-1957) and Topical Files (1942-1962). The Campaign Files include clippings and correspondence from Connable's four campaigns for the office of regent. The Topical Files detail Connable's involvement with the Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions and the labor education program of the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations.
  - Campaign files 1939-1957
    - 1939, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1941, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - 1949, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - 1957, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Topical Files 1942-1957, 1962
    - Correspondence 1944-1957 (Box 1)
    - Regents' Committee on War Activities
      - Report 1942 (Box 1)
      - Papers 1942, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Papers Concerning the Michigan Daily, 1943-1948 (Box 1)
    - Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions
      - Correspondence 1947-1956, 6 folders (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1966-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Speech 1953 (Box 2)
      - Proceedings 1944-1953, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Labor Education Program
      - Correspondence 1946 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1948-1949 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1954, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Business Career
  The Business Career series includes correspondence and newsletters from the Monroe Calculating Machine Company.
  - Clippings 1948-1976 (Box 2)
  - Monroe Calculating Machine Company
    - Correspondence 1949-1956 (Box 2)
    - Keynote (newsletter), 1950-1951, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
    - The Field (newsletter), 1954, 1955, 1957 (Box 2)
- Political Career
  The Political Career series includes Connable's papers on Republican Party activities during 1941-1957. Also included are papers and correspondence concerning Connable's work as the Michigan campaign manager for Republican presidential candidate Wendell L. Willkie, during the years 1943-1944. This series also contains correspondence from 1945-1949 between Connable and Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg, and the contents of a notebook containing information on the 1949 Republican State Convention.
  - Papers Concerning Republican Party Activities 1941-1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Campaign Manager for Wendell L. Willkie: Papers 1943-1944, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Wendell L. Willkie and Willkie Biography: Papers 1944-1954 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg 1945-1949 (Box 2)
  - Republican State Convention 1949, 1 volumes (in folder) (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series contains papers from the Office of Price Administration, in which Connable served as Price Specialist during 1942-1943. Also in this series are various personal clippings and correspondence.
  - Office of Price Administration, Price Specialist Papers 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes personal portraits, group photographs of the Board of Regents and Association of Governing Boards, business achievements, and views of University of Michigan buildings and panoramic campus views (1950s).
  Views of University of Michigan buildings and panoramic campus views (1950s); portraits and group photos of Connable and others relating to his activities as regent.
  - Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions and Board of Regents 1945, 1947, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Business Career 1949-1951, 1960 (Box 2)
  - University Buildings circa 1958 (Box 2)
    (Medical Center, Couzens Hall, Phoenix Memorial Laboratory, Law Quadrangle, Angell Hall, Central Campus, North Campus)
  - Portraits and Miscellaneous (Box 2)